Jai Hind friends, so today we will
talk about the best term insurance and
I have downloaded this Excel sheet from the IRDAI website.
I will give you the link
in the description.  You can also
cross verify this particular analysis yourself by downloading this Excel sheet.
In this you will
see the total claims here.  After that,
you will see Claims Paid visible on the right side.
Here you will see then claims reputed and then claims rejected.
So there is a little fine line between reputed claims and
rejected claims
, there is a difference between the two.  Claims
rejected means that the
claims of the insured are
rejected because
they have not provided full documentation.
They have not provided full information
and have
not taken any action within the timeline.  Therefore
his claim has been turned down now.
But it is possible that in future,
if they provide their documents correctly, then
their claim will be
put back into the process.  But does
claims reputed mean that the
claim you have raised has been
turned down on a permanent basis?  It has been
rejected.  Because your
claim may not be meeting some terms and conditions
and whatever coverage you have taken,
this claim is not coming under that coverage.
So what do most of the companies do?
Such claims are repudiated.  And
this claim reputed and its benefit
amount is the
main issue to be discussed in claim reputed.  Because
when we go to the Policy Bazaar website,
we get
to see the Claim Settlement Ratio there, which is
CSR.  But doesn't CSR give you a clear idea of ​​what the
company is
doing behind the scenes?  The amount settlement ratio gives you the correct idea
because what this
insurance company does is that it
approves small amounts.  Reputates large amounts.
Due to which their CSR
is also maintained and they are
also saved from making big claims.  And
I will tell you how.  Let us assume
that any company has received 10,000
claims and what they have
done is that they have rejected the 100 most expensive
claims outright.
Some people have found faults in you and
rejected it and what they have
done is that they have approved 9900 claims.
So what will become of their CSR?
Their CSR will become 99%.  And they have
rejected these 100 claims, it is
possible that their claim would be worth Rs 1 crore
which they have rejected.
So the CSR
gives you a very fast picture.
You will get the main picture only from the amount settlement ratio.
So let's go back to the Excel sheet.
So in this Excel sheet you can see
that in our country there are a total of
26 life insurance companies which are selling term policies.
But
we will not analyze all this life insurance data.
And our first
parameter will be that we
will analyze the data of such life insurance companies
which have processed more than 3000 claims in the last year.
Because if
your life insurance is processing a claim of less than Rs 3000, then
it means that it is
not spread much across India.
We don't even have much data to
analyze it.  So that's why the
benchmark I have set is 3000 claims.
If you have received 3000 claims in the last year, only then will
I go and
analyse it.  So according to this, you
can see here that there are a total of 13 such
life insurers who have received
claims of more than Rs 3000 in the last year.
You can see here that the total
claims will be visible here and the
claims paid will be visible here
and its CSR ratio will be
visible here.  It is very easy to take out CSR.
If you divide the number of policies approved by them by the total claims rate,
then you will get CSR.
So here you will see the value of total CSR.
Now
if we denotate this CSR ratio on the chart
and if we short it from the top to the minimum, then
you will find that Axis MS Lite has the highest CSR.
After that HTC is coming out.
After that, Bajaj Ali and then PNB Mate
Lite, but friends, again I am telling you
that such shocking
results will come in future that you will lose faith in CSR.
So if we look at this data on the
chart, then you can see here in the chart
that at the top you can
see the chart of Axis with 99.6, after that
HDFC, then Bajaj Reliance, then PNB
and LIC will be visible here
and the lowest CSR is of India First.
So this is your CSR.  But what
I was telling you repeatedly is that I have to find out the
amount settlement ratio.  So
again what I have done is that
I have filtered out the data of all the claims paid by them and all the claims rejected by them.
Just for example, you can see here
that LIC has
paid claims for 829318 policies.  But
they have
either repudiated or
rejected 14884 claims.  And the total
amount that is coming out is Rs 517 crore.
So the amount for which they have
rejected the policy is Rs 3.48 lakh.   That
means, whatever they have rejected or
repudiated, their policy is coming out to be worth ₹3.5 lakh
and whatever they have
approved, it is coming out to be worth ₹15,000.
So there doesn't seem to be much difference in this.  At the
same time, if you
look at HDFC here, the average amount approved by HDFC is
coming out to be ₹8,19,000.  Whatever amount
they have paid against the policy
and what they have rejected,
their average is coming out to be ₹66 lakhs
but the policy which they have rejected.
If we draw this on a chart,
you will see the top four companies here.  First of all, the
name is HDFC.  The
rejection from HDFC and the amount
rejected is coming out to be 66 lakhs.
And how much have they approved
?  Let's approve this for Rs 8 lakh.  Ok?
And the one which is worth Rs 66 lakh or around Rs 1 crore,
because this Rs 66 lakh is an average, it is
rejected.
Tata's is even bigger than this.  Here if you look at Tata, the
approval rate of Tata is around Rs 17 lakh
which is good.
But their average rejection rate is
68 lakh.  That means, if
you have taken Tata term insurance of Rs 60-70 lakh, then
brother, be alert.  You will face a
lot of problems in getting your approval.
And then here you will see that the
average rejection of Max Life is coming to Rs 54 lakh.
So if we look at the CSR of Max Life,
as we saw, Max L
and HDFC have the highest CSR.
Bajaj Reliance has the highest
CSR but their rejections and the
amount hidden behind the rejections are coming out to be the highest.
So here you will see that the
rejection of Bajaj Reliance is also coming out to be an average of ₹34 lakh.  The
approval is coming out to be just ₹4 lakh.  That
means the average of all the policies they
approve is Rs 4 lakh and the
average of all the policies they reject is
approximately Rs 35 lakh.  So
you are seeing this huge difference here
and in HDFC you are
seeing the maximum difference here
because they approve the claims of around Rs 8 lakh
and reject the claims of around Rs 66 lakh
and after that Shriram's difference is also visible here.
So from this amount settlement
ratio and its rejection, we
can confirm that Charap is such a company that
you will have to be cautious before taking term insurance and if you are taking term insurance of a higher amount.
First of all is your Tata, after that
is HDFC, after that is Bajaj Ali,
after that is Maxlife and then is
Shriram, so again I am telling you that
their CSR is the best but their
rejection is such that they are at the forefront in rejecting high amounts.
Now
which one is coming out better than all of these?  So here
you will see that this blue chart and this
green graph, both of them are
visible closest to you in ICICI.
After that, it will also come out to you from LIC.
LIC approves the loan amount which is around Rs 2 lakh
and rejects the one which is around Rs 5 lakh.
After this, the
ratio of SBI is also quite good.
SBI also approves those around Rs 5 lakh
and
rejects those around Rs 10 lakh.  There is a huge difference between the approval and rejection graphs of these four companies,
Bajaj, HDFC, Max Le, Shriram and Tata.
And this is an alarming one.
Therefore, if you are
thinking of taking term insurance from all these companies, then please
think again.  Now let's talk about the
total claim paid percentage.  So what is this claim
paid percentage?  So here
if you check near CSR then
in this graph you will check that for
example the total amount of claims received by HDFC was Rs.
1655 crores
but in that
they have paid only Rs. 1584 crores as claims.
So does this mean that
they have paid 95.7% of the claim amount.
So this amount claim of 95.7% will also be
available from the same website.  This is nothing of my own making.
This 95.7% will also be calculated in the Excel sheet or PDF that you download.  That means
their CSR is 99.5%.  But
how much amount did he pay?  95.7% means that the
actual value of that 5% is
coming out to be 4.3%.  So again, as
I showed you through the graph here,
they have
rejected the big amounts and pay the small
amounts here.  So
if we go to the paid amount, then
you are not able to see Shri Ram here
because if you look at Shri Ram, then
only around 80% of your
payment is coming for Shri Ram.  That's why it hasn't appeared in my chart.
And I don't even want to keep that
because it's so fake coming out of
here.  Now
look back here, I have added CSR along with it.
Here I have
made a line for 95%.  I have marked red here those whose payment is less than 95%.
So coming in that are Aitya
Birla, Bajaj Reliance India FS, Kotak
Mahindra and then Reliance Nipon.  Now,
if I try to compare the claims paid chart with the previous chart of rejections, after removing CSR, then
I see the best data of ICICI coming out here.
After that, I also
like LIC a lot here because
see, LIC gets 8 lakh to 9 lakh claims.
So their ratio is
always a little distorted.
But it looks good to me.
After that, SBI also seems good to me
which will give good performance and after that
PNB Mate Life also seems good to me
but if you look at PNB Mate Life here, then
its average rejection
ratio is around 26 lakhs
whereas the approval is only of 8 lakhs, so in
this way, if we
follow the fundamentals with a little exclusion, then we have to leave HDFC, Bajaj, Reliance Max,
Tata Sam, etc.
blindly and we have to concentrate on three or four more
after that.  First of all,
ICICI will come to you, after that your LIC will come,
after that your SBI will come, after that
you can also consider PNB.  So
friends, this was today's video which was totally an
analysis of the data taken from IRDAI's website.  I hope
you liked today's video.
See you again in the next video.  Till then
friends, Jai